<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<organism-settings>
	<main-form>
		<footer>
		Developed by: Tulio de Oliveira, Koen Deforche, Sharon Cassol, Andrew Rambaut and Anne-Mieke Vandamme.
		</footer>
	</main-form>
	<start-form>
		<title>
		REGA HIV Subtyping Tool Version 2.0
		</title>
		<note>
		This tool is designed to use phylogenetic methods in order to identify the subtype of a specific sequence.
		The sequence is analysed for recombination using bootscanning methods.
		<br/>
		<b>Note for batch analysis:</b> The REGA subtype tool accepts up to 1000 sequences at a time. 
		</note>
	</start-form>
	<monitor-form>
		<title>
		HIV Genotyping Tool Results
		</title>
	</monitor-form>
	<details-form>
		<title>
		HIV Genotyping Details
		</title>
	</details-form>
	<howToCite-form>
		<title>
		How to Cite the REGA HIV-1 Automated Subtyping Tool
		</title>
		<cite>
		<b>These tools are not yet published. In the mean time please cite the following paper:</b>
		<br/>
		<a href="http://bioinformatics.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/bti607v1">An Automated Genotyping System for Analysis of HIV-1 and other Microbial Sequences.</a> 
		<br/>
		T. de Oliveira,K. Deforche, S. Cassol, M. Salminem, D. Paraskevis, C. Seebregts, J. Snoeck, E. J. van Rensburg ,A. M. J. Wensing, D.A. van de Vijver, C. A. Boucher , R. Camacho , and A-M Vandamme.
		<br/>
		Bioinformatics 2005; 21 (19), 3797-3800.
		</cite>
	</howToCite-form>
	<tutorial-form>
		<title>
		HIV-1 Subtying Tutorial
		</title>
		<tutorial-text>
			<text>
			The report contains three main parts: HIV-1 Subtype analysis, CRFs analysis, 
			and Bootscanning (or Phylogenetic signal) analysis.
			The first two areas, show the phylogenetic trees constructed with pure subtypes (part one) and CRFs forms (part two).
			For sequences with more than 1.000 bp a bootscanning analysis is performed and a graphical result displayed,
			for sequences below 1.000 bp the bootscanning is  replaced by phylogenetic signal analysis to determine if the alignment is well suitable for phylogenetic analysis.<br/>
			Multiple sequences can be submitted to the REGA HIV-1 subtyping tool.<br/>
			<b>The batch report </b> (figure1) will be the batch report and contain information on the sequence name, length, assigned subtype and a figure of the HIV-1 genome. Accessing the report link will take the user to a report to each submitted sequence.
			</text>
			<figure>
			files/tutorial_1.gif
			</figure>
			<text>
			<b>The sequence report</b> (figure 2) will be composed of three areas named: sequence assignment, analysis details and phylogenetic analyses.
			<br/>
			The Sequence assignment contains information on:
			<ul style="text-align: left;">
			    <li>the sequence submitted (name and length),</li>
			    <li>the classification assignment (subtype, subgroup and bootstrap support),</li>
			    <li>a graphical representation of the HIV-1 genome showing the genomic region of the query sequence with the start and end positions related to the HXB2 genome,</li>
			    <li>the motivation of the classification (this is based on the decision tree).</li>
			</ul>
			The Phylogenetic analysis section contains:
			<ul style="text-align: left;">
			    <li>the phylogenetic tree in PDF and Nexus format,</li>
			    <li>the log file generated by PAUP (contains info on the model of evolution and its parameters),</li>
			    <li>the alignment used.</li>
		    </ul>
			</text>
			<figure>
			files/tutorial_2.gif
			</figure>
		</tutorial-text>
	</tutorial-form>
	<decisionTrees-form>
		<title>
			REGA HIV-1 Subtying Classification Rules
		</title>
		<decisionTrees-text>
			<header>
			Decision Tree for sequences longer than 800 bp
			</header>
			<figure>
			files/decisionTrees_1.gif
			</figure>			
			<figure>
			files/decisionTrees_2.gif
			</figure>
			<rule number="Rule 1A" name="PURE">
			Subtype assigned based on sequence &gt; 800 bps, clustering with a pure subtype with bootstrap &gt; 70% without recombination in the bootscan, and do not clustering with a CRF with bootstrap &gt;70 %.
			</rule>
			<rule number="Rule 1B" name="PURE">
			Subtype assigned based on sequence &gt; 800 bps, clustering with a pure subtype with bootstrap &gt; 70% without recombination in the bootscan,  clustering with a CRF with bootstrap &gt;70 % however  not clustering inside the CRF cluster.
			</rule>
			<rule number="Rule 1C" name="PURE (CRF)">
			Subtype assigned based on sequence &gt; 800 bps, clustering with a pure subtype with bootstrap &gt; 70% without recombination in the bootscan,  clustering with a CRF with bootstrap &gt;70 % and clustering inside the pure subtype cluster.
			</rule>
			<rule number="Rule 2" name="check the bootscan">
			Subtype unassigned based on sequence &gt; 800bp, clustering with a pure subtype with bootstrap &gt;70 %, with detection of recombination in the pure subtype bootscan, and failure to classify as a CRFs (bootstrap support).
			</rule>
			<rule number="Rule 3" name="check the bootscan">
			Subtype unassigned based on sequence &gt; 800bp, clustering with a pure subtype and CRF with bootstrap &gt;70 %, with detection of recombination in the pure subtype bootscan, and failure to classify as a CRFs (bootscan support).
			</rule>
			<rule number="Rule 4" name="CRF">
			Subtype assigned based on sequence &gt; 800bp, clustering with a CRF with bootstrap &gt; 70%,with detection of recombination in the pure subtype bootscan, and further confirmed as a CRF by bootscan analysis.
			</rule>
			<rule number="Rule 5" name="check the report">
			Subtype unassigned based on sequence &gt; 800bp, do not clustering with a pure subtype with bootstrap &gt;70 %, with no detection of recombination in the pure subtype bootscan.
			</rule>
			<rule number="Rule 6" name="check the bootscan">
			Subtype unassigned based on sequence &gt; 800bp, do not clustering with a pure subtype or CRF with bootstrap &gt;70 %, with detection of recombination.
			</rule>
			<rule number="Rule 7" name="check the bootscan">
			Subtype unassigned based on sequence &gt; 800bp, clustering with a CRF with bootstrap &gt; 70%,with detection of recombination in the pure subtype bootscan, and failure to classify as a CRFs (bootscan support).
			</rule>
			<rule number="Rule 8" name="CRF">
			Subtype assigned based on sequence &gt; 800bp, clustering with a CRF with bootstrap &gt; 70%,with detection of recombination in the pure subtype bootscan, and further confirmed by CRF by bootscan analysis.
			</rule>
			<header>
			Decision Tree for sequences shorter than 800 bp
			</header>
			<figure>
			files/decisionTrees_3.gif
			</figure>
			<rule number="Rule 9" name="check the report">
			Subtype unassigned based on sequence &lt; 800bp, do not clustering with a pure subtype with bootstrap &gt;70 %.
			</rule>
			<rule number="Rule 10" name="check the report">
			Subtype unassigned based on sequence &lt; 800bp, clustering with a pure subtype with bootstrap &gt; 70%, however  not clustering inside the pure subtype cluster.
			</rule>
			<rule number="Rule 11" name="Pure">
			Subtype assigned based on sequence &lt; 800bp, clustering with a pure subtype with bootstrap &gt; 70%, and clustering inside the pure subtype cluster 
			</rule>
		</decisionTrees-text>
	</decisionTrees-form>
</organism-settings>