<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<messages>
	<message id="main">
		<div class="azure">
			<div class="rivm-header">
				<div id="logo">
					<a href="${app.url}">
						<img src="${app.url}/../../pics/aedesviruses/aedesviruses.png" alt="RIVM Logo" > </img>
					</a>
				</div>
				<div id="application">
					<span id="name">Zika Virus Typing Tool</span>
					<span id="info">Version 0.9 - Alpha </span>
				</div>
				<div class="nav_bar">
					${navigation class="nav_main"}
				</div>
				
				<div id="navigation-bottom" >
				</div>
			</div>
			${content class="content"}
	
			<div class="footer">
				<br/><p>Developed by: <b>FIOCRUZ/Bahia, Brazil</b> (Maria Inés Restovic, Marta Giovanetti, Vagner Fonseca, Murilo Freire, Luiz Alcantara),  <b>KU Leuven, Belgium</b> (Kristof Theys, Pieter Libin, Lize Cuypers, Ana Abecasis, Anne-Mieke Vandamme), <b>Oxford, U.K.</b> (Nuno Faria and Oliver Pybus),  <b>Evandro Chagas Institute, Brazil</b> (Marcio Roberto Teixeira Nunes), <b>CDC/OID/NCEZID</b> (Gilberto A. Santiago), <b>Emweb bvba, Belgium</b> (Koen Deforche) and <b>Africa Centre/UKZN, South Africa</b> (Tulio de Oliveira).</p>
			    <p><b>Contact:</b> <a href="http://www.bahia.fiocruz.br/?area=02X01X11">Dr. Luiz Carlos Junior Alcantara</a>, <a href="http://www.iec.pa.gov.br/index.php/gcPagina/index/56">Dr. Marcio Roberto Teixeira Nunes</a>,<a href="http://evolve.zoo.ox.ac.uk"> Dr. Nuno Faria</a>  and/or <a href="http://www.bioafrica.net/people.php?peopleid=1">Prof. Tulio de Oliveira</a></p> <br/>	
			    <div style="background-color:#FFFFFF">
			    <img src="${app.url}/../../pics/aedesviruses/logobottom.png" alt="Institutions Logo" ></img>
			    </div>
			    <script src="http://www.google-analytics.com/urchin.js" type="text/javascript">
					</script>
					<script type="text/javascript">
						_uacct = "UA-4841045-1";
						urchinTracker();
					</script>
			</div>
	
			<div class="rivm-footer">
				<div>
				</div>
			</div>
		</div>
	</message>

  	<message id="start-form">
  		<div class="start-form form">
		    <h1>Zika Virus Typing Tool Version 0.9 - Alpha </h1>
		    <div class="note">
 				<div>
					This tool is designed to use Blast and phylogenetic methods in order to identify the Zika Virus serotypes and genotypes of a nucleotide sequence.
				</div>
      			<div>
      				<b>Note for batch analysis:</b> The tool accepts up to ${maxAllowedSeqs} sequences at a time. 
				</div>
	 	   </div>
	 	   
	 	   <div class="seqInput">
				${tr:sequenceInput.inputSequenceInFastaFormat}
				<div>
					${fasta-field}
				</div>
				${analyze-button}
				${clear-button}
				${error-text class="error"}
		
				${tr:sequenceInput.uploadSequenceInFastaFormat}

				${file-upload-button}

				${tr:startForm.monitorJob}

				${tr:startForm.labelJobId} ${job-id-field}	${search-button}
			</div>
		</div>
	</message>
	
	<message id="sequenceInput.run">Start!</message>
	<message id="startForm.monitor">Go!</message>
	<message id="sequenceInput.example">&gt;KR815989_Brazil_2015
ACTGGGACTCCACACTGGAACAACAAAGAAGCACTGGTAGAGTTCAAGGACGCACATGCCAAAAGGCA
AACTGTCGTGGTTCTAGGGAGTCAAGAAGGAGCAGTTCACACGGCCCTTGCTGGAGCTCTGGAGGCTG
AGATGGATGGTGCAAAGGGAAGGCTGTCCTCTGGCCACTTGAAATGTCGCCTGAAAATGGATAAACTT
AGATTGAAGGGCGTGTCATACTCCTTGTGTACCGCAGCGTTCACATTCACCAAGATCCCGGCTGAAAC
ACTGCACGGGACAGTCACAGTGGAGGTACAGTACGCAGGGACAGATGGACCTTGCAAG
	</message>

	<message id="job-overview-form">
	  	<div class="monitor-form form">
		    <h1>Zika Virus Typing Tool Results</h1>

		    <div class="info">
				<p>You may bookmark this page to revisit results of this job (${job-id}) later.</p>
				<p>A whole genome typing will take approximately 60 seconds, please be patient.</p>
				
				<p>${analysis-cancelled}</p>

				<div class="analysisProgress">
					${analysis-in-progress}
				</div>
			</div>

			<div>
				${results class="jobTable"}
			</div>

			<div class="downloads">
				${downloads}
			</div>
		</div>
	</message>

  	<message id="details-form">
		<h1>Zika Virus Genotyping Details</h1>
		${details-form}
	</message>
  
  	<message id="generic-details">
  		<div>
  			<div>
  				<div>
					  <div class="dsa-text">
						<span class="label">Name:</span> ${xpath "/genotype_result/sequence/@name"}
						<span class="label">Length:</span> ${xpath "/genotype_result/sequence/@length"}
					</div>
				</div>
				<div>
					<h3>Virus assignment</h3>
					<p>
						<span class="label">Virus assignment:</span><span class="nov-genotype"> ${xpath "/genotype_result/sequence/result[@id='blast']/cluster/concluded-name"}</span>
					</p>
					<p>
						<span class="label"></span>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div>
					<h3>Serotype/Clade and Genotype result</h3>
					<p>
						<span class="label">Serotype/Clade assignment:</span>
						<span class="nov-genotype">${xpath "/genotype_result/sequence/conclusion[@id='type']/assigned/name"}</span>
					</p>
  					<p>
  						<span class="label"></span>
  						<span>${xpath "/genotype_result/sequence/conclusion[@id='type']/motivation"}</span>
					</p>


					${eval-xpath "/genotype_result/sequence/conclusion[@id='subtype']"}
					${<if-defined>}
					    <p>
   							<span class="label">Genotype:</span>
							${eval-xpath "/genotype_result/sequence/conclusion[@id='subtype']"}
							${<if-defined>}
								${eval-xpath "/genotype_result/sequence/conclusion[@type='simple' and @id='subtype']"}
	   							<span class="nov-genotype">
									${<if-defined>}
		   								${xpath "/genotype_result/sequence/conclusion[@id='type']/assigned/name"}
									${</if-defined>}
									${xpath "/genotype_result/sequence/conclusion[@id='subtype']/assigned/name"}
								</span>
							${</if-defined>}
							${<if-not-defined>}
								<span class="nov-genotype">N/A</span>
							${</if-not-defined>}
	  					</p>
						<p>
   							<span class="label"></span>
							${eval-xpath "/genotype_result/sequence/conclusion[@id='subtype']"}
							${<if-defined>}
	   							<span>${xpath "/genotype_result/sequence/conclusion[@id='subtype']/motivation"}</span>
   							${</if-defined>}
   							${<if-not-defined>}
   								<span>Sequence does not sufficiently overlap with region or subcluster is not available for the type</span>
   							${</if-not-defined>}
						</p>
	  				${</if-defined>}
  
 				</div>
 				<div>
 					<h3>Genome region</h3>
 				</div>
 				
 				${genome-img}

 				<div>
					<p class="refseq">
   						Your sequence starts at position ${xpath "/genotype_result/sequence/result[@id='blast']/start"} and finishes at position ${xpath "/genotype_result/sequence/result[@id='blast']/end"} relative to the ${xpath "/genotype_result/sequence/result[@id='blast']/refseq"} reference sequence.
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</div>
	</message>
  
  	<message id="details.phylo-major.title">
  		Phylogenetic Analysis Details (Serotype)
  	</message>

  	<message id="details.phylo-minor.title">
  		Phylogenetic Analysis Details (Genotyping)
  	</message>
  
	<message id="job-overview-downloads">
		<div class="downloadContainer">
			<span>Download results:</span> ${xml-file} ${xls-file} ${csv-file} ${fasta-file}
		</div>
	</message>
	
	<message id="monitorForm.analysisCancelled"><p><b>This job was cancelled!</b></p></message>

	<message id="tool.title">Zika Virus Typing Tool</message>

	<message id="table.header.name">Name</message>
	<message id="table.header.length">Length</message>
	<message id="table.header.blast">Virus</message>
	<message id="table.header.phylo">Phylo</message>
	<message id="table.header.report">Report</message>
	<message id="table.header.genome">Genome</message>

	<message id="how-to-cite-doc">
		<div class="form">
			<h1>How to Cite the Zika Virus Typing Tool</h1>

			<p>Manuscript in preparation.</p>
		    <p>
			For the mean time, please cite:<br/>
				<ul>
					<li> Zika Virus Typing Tool (2015), available at <a href="http://www.bioafrica.net/software.php">www.bioafrica.net/software.php</a></li>

				</ul>
		      	</p>

			
			<p>
			Funded by:<br/>
				<ul>
					<li>VIROGENESIS: Virus discovery and epidemic tracing from high throughput metagenomic sequencing. HORIZON 2020, European Commission.</li>
					<li>Ciencias Sem Fronteiras, CNPQ, Brazil.</li>
					<li>SA MRC Flagship Program, South Africa.</li>

				</ul>
		      	</p>

		</div>
	</message>
	

	<message id="introduction-doc">
		<div class="form">
			<h1>The Zika Virus Typing Tool: Introduction.</h1>

<p>Recently, an increasing number of outbreaks of Dengue, Chikungunya and Zika have been reported in tropical and sub-tropical areas of the globe. The same vectors (Ae. aegypti or Ae. albopictus), which are widely adapted and distributed on a global scale, transmit the Dengue (DENV), Zika (ZIKV) and Chikungunya (CHIKV) viruses. Outbreaks can happen in the same geographical area at the same time, making the differential diagnostic a difficult task for front line heath personnel and the health authorities.</p>
<p>With the advent of next generation sequencing methods, thousands of complete DENV genomes, as well as the first few complete sequences of CHIKV and ZIKV are now available. In this context, we have used the available data to develop an automated computational algorithm to be used for accurate and rapid identification of these virus pathogens. In order to make classification consistent, we also present a detailed description of the methods for amplification and genotyping that are most appropriate to accurately classify those pathogens. The computational and laboratory methods are made freely available in an open source platform and should allow high-throughput and timely identification of the pathogens to strain level. These advances should have major importance for clinical management of patients and strategic decisions of health authorities. </p>


			<h1>Dengue Serotypes and Genotypes</h1>
<p>The definition of a dengue genotype is based on old studies with partial sequencing and sequenced strains in the public domain. Time has passed and the virus has diverged into more complex lineages. We consider that the virus will continue to evolve and new lineages might turn into new serotypes and genotypes in time. We also consider a wide diversity of variables to define a genotype, i.e. monophily, pairwise distance within group and between groups, net genetic diversity within groups, etc. </p>

<p>We understand that there is no good consensus in the dengue world for naming genotypes. The global spread of the virus has made the previous naming of genotypes by geographic association irrelevant. DENV-1, -3, and -4 have genotypes names by roman numerals (i.e. I, II, III, etc.) but there are still publications with contrasting classifications. </p>

<p>Geographic association names DENV-2 genotypes. Considering that geographic association of certain genotypes might be too difficult, we find that using roman numerals (i.e. I, II, III, etc.) could be more appropriate. In addition, a numeral system might also be beneficial to stay in structure with new diverging lineages and genotypes. However, in our tool we still maintain geographic association names for DENV-2 (e.g. like the SE Asia and American genotypes of DEN2) as researchers that deal the public health issue are accustomed to these designations.</p>

<p>
				We have carefully selected reference sequences that represent the diversity of each genotype. In addition, we performed extensive testing to be sure that our reference strains accurately classify other sequences.<br/>
				<ul>
					<li>We include serotypes 1, 2, 3 and 4.</li>
					<li>Serotype 1 includes 1I ,1II, 1III, 1IV and 1V genotypes.</li>
					<li>Serotype 2 includes 2I (American), 2II (Cosmopolitan), 2III (Southern Asian-American), 2IV (Asian II), 2V (Asian I) and 2VI (Sylvatic) genotypes.</li>
					<li>Serotype 3 includes 3I, 3II, 3III and 3V genotypes.</li>
					<li>Serotype 4 includes 4I, 4II, 4III and 4IV genotypes.</li>	
				</ul>
		      	</p>

	       	<p>Partial vs. whole genome. Whole genome sequences (WGS) are not commonly produced for epidemiological purpose or are available in the public domain. Most of the WGS came from the GRID consortium sponsored by the Broad Institute of Harvard and MIT a few years ago. As a result of this project, collaborating sites deposited hundreds of WGS in GenBank, however, redundancy still exists in these datasets, i. e. many samples from one region, same year. There is consensus that the envelope glycoprotein gene (E) is good for phylogenetic classification. This gene has been very effective since it contains sufficient phylogenetic signal (1,485bp) to identify dengue from other viruses and differentiate between serotypes and genotypes. Phylogenetic trees inferred with E gene sequence data generate topologies very similar to whole genome trees. Therefore, investigators working with dengue sequence can expect a similar accuracy for classification of WGS and E gene.</p>
      		      						<p style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0px">
		<img src="${app.url}/../../pics/dengue/DengueWGSdraft1.png" alt="Zika Virus phylogenetic tree" > </img><br/>	
				Fig. 1. Zika Virus phylogenetic tree for WGS and E gene		
	       	</p>
	       				<h1>Chikungunya phylotypes</h1>
<p>The definition of a  Chikungunya genotype is based on the identification of well defined phylogenetic clusters that its origin has been associated to a given geographic region.  </p>

<p>
				We have carefully analysed all of GHIKV whole genomes and reviewed in the literature in order to represent the diversity of each phylotype. In addition, we performed extensive testing to be sure that our reference strains accurately classify other sequences.<br/>
				<ul>
					<li>We include 3 phylotypes</li>
					<li>Phylotype 1 includes sequences from Asian and Caribbean</li>
					<li>Phylotype 2 includes sequences from East-Central-South-African.</li>
					<li>Phylotype 3 includes sequences West Africa</li>
				</ul>
		      	</p>
		      		<p style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0px">
					<img src="${app.url}/../../pics/dengue/chikvWGSdraft1.png" alt="Zika Virus phylogenetic tree" > </img><br/>	
				Fig. 2. Chikungunya &amp; Viruses phylogenetic tree for WGS and E gene		
	       	</p>
		      
		      	       				<h1>Zika Virus phylotypes</h1>
<p>The definition of a Zika genotype is based on the identification of well defined phylogenetic clusters that its origin has been associated to a given geographic region.  </p>

<p>
				We have carefully analysed all of ZIKV whole genomes and reviewed in the literature in order to represent the diversity of each phylotype. In addition, we performed extensive testing to be sure that our reference strains accurately classify other sequences. We found that the whole genome and the Envelope gene (E) gene to be suitable for classification <br/>
				<ul>
					<li>We include 3 phylotypes</li>
					<li>Phylotype 1 includes sequences from deferent African countries</li>
					<li>Phylotype 2 includes sequences from Asian origin</li>
					<li>Phylotype 3 includes a recently published Senegalese whole genome, which is very divergent from other African ones (Faye et al. PLoS
Negl Trop Dis 2014, 8(1): e2636)</li>
					<li>The phylogenies are rooted with Spondweni virus </li>
				</ul>
		      	</p>
		      		<p style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0px">
					<img src="${app.url}/../../pics/dengue/chikvWGSdraft1.png" alt="Zika Virus phylogenetic tree" > </img><br/>	
				Fig. 2. Chikungunya &amp; Viruses phylogenetic tree for WGS and E gene		
	       	</p>
		      		
		      	
		      	
      </div>
	</message>
      
    <message id="how-to-use-doc">
		<div class="form">
			<h1>Zika Virus Typing Tool Tutorial</h1>
			
			<p>
				One or more (up to 20.000 per run) Dengue sequences can be pasted (A) or uploaded (B) in Fasta format (see Fig. 1).
			 	Sequences of all regions of the Dengue genome can be used.
			</p>
			<p>
				When pasting a single sequence the Identifier of the sequence (>Sequencename) should be included (Fasta format).
				One example sequence is present as a default. A set of <a href="#/examples">three example sequences</a> is also available.
			</p> 

			<p style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0px">
		<img src="${app.url}/../../pics/dengue/FigEntry.png" alt="The startingpage of the typing tools" > </img><br/>	
				Fig. 1. The startingpage of the Dengue typingtool
			</p>

			<p>
				The analysis takes up to a few seconds per sequence. Thus, for large batches the run can be viewed later,
				by typing the Job-Id at C. Here also runs by others can be viewed, if the Job-Id has been communicated.
				Runs are kept on the server for 1 week.
			</p> 

			<p style="text-align: center; margin: 20px 0px">
		<img src="${app.url}/../../pics/dengue/DENVFigResults.png" alt="The startingpage of the typing tools" > </img><br/>	
				Fig. 2. Overview of the results
			</p>

			<p>
				After the 'Start' button is pushed the analysis is started and after a few seconds the results overview is shown (Fig. 2).
				While the analysis is still in progress the following message is displayed: 'Analysis in progress... (Showing partial results).
				This page will be automatically updated every 5 seconds...'.
			</p>

			<p>
				The Job Id number, which can be used to retrieve the results later is displayed at the top of the page as soon as the job is started.
				<br/>
				For each sequence the length, positioning on the Dengue genome and assigned genotype are determined.<br/>
				After the complete analysis is finished the analysis results can be downloaded as XML, CSV or Excel file.<br/>
				For each sequence more details can be viewed in the individual reports by clicking on 'report' in the results table.<br/>
			</p>
			
			<p>
				The report of the genotyping details per sequence contains a brief overview of the assignment, followed by details of the phylogenetic
				analysis including a phylogenetic tree.<br/>
				The report contains information on:
				<ul>
					<li>The sequence submitted (name and length)</li>
					<li>Blast result: The genus/species (Dengue species) of the submitted sequence</li>
					<li>Phylo result: For Dengue sequences, the genotype assignment</li>
					<li>The robustness of the phylogenetic assignment using bootstrap values. Only with bootstrap > 70 a genotype
						or variant is assigned.</li>
					<li>A graphical representation of the Dengue genome showing the genomic region of the query sequence with the start and
						end positions related to the Dengue reference sequence.</li>
					<li>A NJ tree is computed with the submitted sequence at the top.</li>
					<li>The bootstrap tree can be viewed and downloaded in the PAUP* log file</li>
					<li>The alignment can be downloaded in NEXUS or FASTA format</li>
				</ul>
			</p>

			<p>
				No genotype is assigned if:
				<ul>
					<li>The submitted sequence belongs to another Flavivirus genus. In this case the genus is indicated and the analysis stops.</li>
					<li>The submitted sequence is shorter than 100 bp. In this case only assignment of the species (Dengue) is possible.</li>
					<li>The bootstrap value &lt; 70. In this case an alignment and a NJ tree are produced which can be used to get an indication of
						the phylogeny.</li>
				</ul>
			</p> 
		</div>
    </message>

 	<message id="examples-doc">
		<div class="form">
			<h1>Example Sequences for the Zika Virus Typing Tool</h1>
	        
	        <div class="sequenceName">&gt;AB908162_Tahiti_2014</div>
			<div class="sequence">
TCCAGGCTTTACCATAATGGCCGCAATCCTGGCATACACCATAGGAACGACGCATTTCCAAAGAGTCC
TGATATTCATCCTACTGACAGCCATCGCTCCTTCAATGACAATGCGCTGCATAGGAATATCAAATAGG
GACTTTGTGGAAGGAGTGTCAGGAGGGAGTTGGGTTGACATAGTTTTAGAACATGGAAGTTGTGTGAC
GACGATGGCAAAAAATAAACCAACACTGGACTTTGAACTGATAAAAACAGAAGCCAAACAACCCGCCA
CCTTAAGGAAGTACTGTATAGAGGCTAAACTGACCAACACGACAACAGACTCGCGCTGCCCAACACAA
GGGGAACCCACCCTGAATGAAGAGCAGGACAAAAGGTTTGTCTGCAAACATTCTATGGTAGACAGAGG
ATGGGGAAATGGATGTGGATTGTTTGGAAAAGGAGGCATCGTGACCTGTGCTATGTTCACATGCAAAA
AGAACATGGAAGGGAAAATTGTGCAGCCAGAAAACCTGGAATACACTGTCGTGATAACACCTCATTCA
GGGGAAGAACATGCAGTCGGAAATGACACAGGAAAACATGGTAAAGAAGTCAAGATAACACCACAGAG
CTCCATCACAGAGGCGGAACTGACAGGCTATGGCACTGTTACGATGGAGTGCTCTCCAAGAACGGGCC
TCGACTTCAATGAGATGGTGTTGCTGCAAATGGAAGACAAAGCTTGGCTGGTGCACAGACAATGGTTC<br/>

	        </div>
	        
	        <div class="sequenceName">&gt;KR815989_Brazil_2015</div>
			<div class="sequence">
ACTGGGACTCCACACTGGAACAACAAAGAAGCACTGGTAGAGTTCAAGGACGCACATGCCAAAAGGCA
AACTGTCGTGGTTCTAGGGAGTCAAGAAGGAGCAGTTCACACGGCCCTTGCTGGAGCTCTGGAGGCTG
AGATGGATGGTGCAAAGGGAAGGCTGTCCTCTGGCCACTTGAAATGTCGCCTGAAAATGGATAAACTT
AGATTGAAGGGCGTGTCATACTCCTTGTGTACCGCAGCGTTCACATTCACCAAGATCCCGGCTGAAAC
ACTGCACGGGACAGTCACAGTGGAGGTACAGTACGCAGGGACAGATGGACCTTGCAAG

			</div>
				        <div class="sequenceName">&gt;EU545988_Uganda_2008</div>
			<div class="sequence">
ATGAAAAACCCCAAAGAAGAAATCCGGAGGATCCGGATTGTCAATATGCTAAAACGCGGAGTAGCCCGTG
TGAGCCCCTTTGGGGGCTTGAAGAGGCTGCCAGCCGGACTTCTGCTGGGTCATGGGCCCATCAGGATGGT
CTTGGCGATACTAGCCTTTTTGAGATTCACGGCAATCAAGCCATCACTGGGTCTCATCAATAGATGGGGT
TCAGTGGGGAAAAAAGAGGCTATGGAAATAATAAAGAAGTTCAAGAAAGATCTGGCTGCCATGCTGAGAA
TAATCAATGCTAGGAAGGAGAAGAAGAGACGAGGCACAGATACTAGTGTCGGAATTGTTGGCCTCCTGCT
GACCACAGCCATGGCAGTGGAGGTCACTAGACGTGGGAGTGCATACTATATGTACTTGGACAGAAGCGAT
GCTGGGGAGGCCATATCTTTTCCAACCACACTGGGGATGAACAAGTGTTACATACAGATCATGGATCTTG
GACACATGTGTGATGCCACCATGAGCTATGAATGCCCTATGTTGGATGAGGGGGTAGAACCAGATGACGT
CGATTGTTGGTGCAACACGACATCAACTTGGGTTGTGTACGGAACCTGCCACCACAAAAAAGGTGAAGCA
CGGAGATCTAGAAGAGCTGTGACGCTCCCCTCCCATTCCACTAGGAAGCTGCAAACGCGGTCGCAGACCT
<br/>

	        </div>
    	</div>
  	</message>
</messages>
